export const GEOGRAPHYA2013 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. The scale of the map in Representative Fraction (RF) is",
A: "1:300,000",
B: "1:200,000",
C: "1:100,000",
D: "1:80,000",
answer: "C. 1:100,000",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The feature marked X in the Southern part of the map is a",
A: "Ridge",
B: "Cuesta",
C: "Valley",
D: "Knoll",
answer: "C. Valley",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. What is the relief feature in the space marked S in the South Western part of the map?",
A: "Pass",
B: "Saddle",
C: "Col",
D: "Knoll",
answer: "A. Pass",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. What is the main occupation of the people of OWO settlement?",
A: "Farming",
B: "Mining",
C: "Fishing",
D: "Trading",
answer: "B. Mining",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. Which of the following will most likely do well around lkpa settlement?",
A: "Sodium",
B: "Millet",
C: "Rice",
D: "Guinea corn",
answer: "C. Rice",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. AWA settlement can be described as",
A: "mining settlement",
B: "Industrial settlement",
C: "Confluence settlement",
D: "Port settlement",
answer: "D. Port settlement",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Which of the following is likely to be an economic activity in the South Eastern part of the mapped area?",
A: "lumbering",
B: "animal rearing",
C: "mining",
D: "wood carving",
answer: "A. lumbering",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Through what mode of transport will a visitor from lkpa settlement arrive at AWA scnlemeñt?",
A: "Air",
B: "Road",
C: "Rail",
D: "Water",
answer: "D. Water",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. What is the bearing of Ise from Ogah?",
A: "100",
B: "400",
C: "700",
D: "2100",
answer: "B. 40",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. AWA town performs educational function because",
A: "It is a university town",
B: "Of the presence of school",
C: "It has a research institute",
D: "It has a school of aviation",
answer: "B. Of the presence of school",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Which of the following is at the centre of the solar system?",
A: "The earth",
B: "The moon",
C: "The sun",
D: "The stars",
answer: "C. The sun",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. How many standard time zones will a country with a longitudinal extent of 120’ have?",
A: "Six",
B: "Eight",
C: "Nine",
D: "zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz",
answer: "B. Eight",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. The shape of the earth can be described as",
A: "flat",
B: "spherical",
C: "circular",
D: "spheroidal",
answer: "B. spherical",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. Which latitudes mark the limits of the overhead sun’s apparent movement north and south of the Equator?",
A: "Horse latitudes",
B: "Tropics of cancer and Capricorn",
C: "Doldrums",
D: "Arctic and Antarctic circles",
answer: "B. Tropics of cancer and Capricorn",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Plutonic rocks are igneous rocks that have hardened",
A: "On the earth’s surface",
B: "On the top of the volcanoes",
C: "In temperate seas",
D: "Beneath the earth’s surface",
answer: "D. Beneath the earth’s surface",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. What relief feature is formed when magma cut across the layers of sedimentary rocks?",
A: "Dyke",
B: "Sill",
C: "Laccolith",
D: "Batholith",
answer: "A. Dyke",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. What is the name of the raised portions of Fold Mountains?",
A: "Synclines",
B: "Pediments",
C: "Graben",
D: "Anticlines",
answer: "D. Anticlines",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. When magma intrudes into horizontal cracks in the bedrock, it forms",
A: "dyke",
B: "sill",
C: "batholith",
D: "lava plateau",
answer: "B. sill",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Into what metamorphic rock is chalk and limestone changed during the process of metamorphism?",
A: "slate",
B: "marble",
C: "quartzite",
D: "gneiss",
answer: "B. marble",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. In which of the following layers of the atmosphere does temperature decrease with altitude?",
A: "troposphere",
B: "ionosphere",
C: "thermosphere",
D: "exosphere",
answer: "A. troposphere",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Which of the following features in the Ocean Basin is the Mariana Trench?",
A: "A deep sea plain",
B: "A continental slope",
C: "A continental shelf",
D: "An ocean deep -",
answer: "D. An ocean deep",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Where is the abyssal plain found?",
A: "On the ocean floor",
B: "On submerged coastlands",
C: "In the middle course of a river",
D: "In limestone regions",
answer: "A. On the ocean floor",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. What is the name of the permeable rock layer which lies between the layers of impermeable rock in an artesian basin?",
A: "Oasis",
B: "Water shed",
C: "Aquifer",
D: "Channel",
answer: "C. Aquifer",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Which of the following months is hottest at station X?",
A: "November",
B: "May",
C: "March",
D: "January",
answer: "A. November",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The method used for illustration of the statistics for station X is?",
A: "complex graph",
B: "pie chart",
C: "histogram",
D: "simple line graph",
answer: "D. simple line graph",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. What is the annual range of temperature for station X?",
A: "11oC",
B: "21oC",
C: "3OoC",
D: "36o C",
answer: "B. 21oC",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. The range of temperature in coastal areas is smaller than that of inland areas because",
A: "the sea has a moderating influence on coastal temperature",
B: ". coastal areas are constantly hotter than inlands",
C: "coastal areas are drier",
D: "rainfall along the coast is lower",
answer: "A. the sea has a moderating influence on coastal temperature",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The extension of the desert to areas that were originally not desert is called desert",
A: "penetration",
B: "encroachment",
C: "movement",
D: "invasion",
answer: "B. encroachment",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. The transfer of energy from one trophic level to another within an ecosystem is referred to as",
A: "Food chain",
B: "Carbon cycle",
C: "Nitrogen cycle",
D: "Ecosystem interaction",
answer: "A. Food chain",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. The cooling of a warm moist air current as it passes over a cold sea or land surface often causes",
A: "Hailstones.",
B: "Fog.",
C: "Sleet.",
D: "High tides",
answer: "B. Fog.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. In what unit is relative humidity expressed?",
A: "Percentage",
B: "zzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzzz",
C: "Kilogram",
D: "Degrees Fahrenheit",
answer: "A. Percentage",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Which of the following refers to soil profile?",
A: "The shape of the land",
B: "The vertical section of the soil",
C: "The mineral composition of the soil",
D: "The parent material component of the soil",
answer: "B. The vertical section of the soil",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. “It is fine in texture, with small pore spaces and is poorly aerated “Which of the following soil types does this statement describe?",
A: "Clayey soil",
B: "Loamy soil",
C: "Lateritic soil",
D: "Sandy soil",
answer: "A. Clayey soil",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. “It is characterized by the presence of abundant grass with scattered trees”. This statement describes",
A: "Rainforest vegetation",
B: "Savanna vegetation",
C: "Temperate forest",
D: "Coniferous forest",
answer: "B. Savanna vegetation",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. What is an association or group of plants growing together in a particular habitat called?",
A: "Vegetation",
B: "Botany",
C: "Biosphere",
D: "Lithosphere",
answer: "A. Vegetation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. In which of the following regions will chemical weathering occur throughout the year?",
A: "the Mediterranean",
B: "Tropical continental",
C: "Equatorial",
D: "Temperate continental",
answer: "C. Equatorial",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. The position of Africa from 37oN to 35oS of the Equator makes it the most",
A: "Tropical of all the continents",
B: "Polar of all the continents",
C: "Temperate of all the continents",
D: "Sub-temperate of all the continents",
answer: "A. Tropical of all the continents",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Which of the following is a distinguishing feature of a rural settlement?",
A: "Large aerial coverage",
B: "Many social amenities",
C: "Primary economic activities",
D: "People of different cultural backgrounds",
answer: "C. Primary economic activities",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. The following are factors responsible for migration except",
A: "Natural disaster",
B: "Population pressure on land",
C: "Age of natives",
D: "Changes in status",
answer: "D. Changes in status",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. The busiest ocean trade route is the",
A: "Suez Canal route",
B: "Panama Canal route",
C: "Cape route",
D: "North Atlantic route",
answer: "D. North Atlantic route",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. When the value of a country’s exports equals the value of her import, she has achieved",
A: "balance of trade",
B: "favourable trade",
C: "barter trade",
D: "world trade",
answer: "A. balance of trade",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. Which of the following situations refer to optimum population?",
A: "When the resources and population are in equilibrium",
B: "When the population far exceeds its resources",
C: "When the resources far exceeds population",
D: "When the resources for the rural population is abundant",
answer: "A. When the resources and population are in equilibrium",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Which of the following countries has the highest population density?",
A: "Mali",
B: "North Korea",
C: "Java",
D: "Malaysia",
answer: "C. Java",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. In which of the following industry type is copper commonly used as raw material?",
A: "Chemical industry",
B: "Wood processing industry",
C: "Cement industry",
D: "Electrical industry",
answer: "D. Electrical industry",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Which of the following areas is the best location for cement industry?",
A: "Near the market",
B: "At the source of power",
C: "Near the source of raw material",
D: "Where labour is abundant",
answer: "C. Near the source of raw material",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. In which of the following plant communities can oak, olive, fir, cedar, laurel and rosemary be commonly found?",
A: "Mediterranean woodland",
B: "Tropical rainforest",
C: "Cool temperate forest",
D: "Tropical woodland",
answer: "A. Mediterranean woodland",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. Which of the following cities is most important for gold mining in Africa?",
A: "Jos",
B: "Banjul",
C: "Pretoria",
D: "Johannesburg",
answer: "D. Johannesburg",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. The following are importance of gold mining to South Africa except",
A: "Generation of revenue",
B: "Collapse of the roof of the mines",
C: "Development of great cities",
D: "Provision of employment for people",
answer: "C. Development of great cities",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Which of the following account for the high irrigation farming in the northern parts of West Africa?",
A: "Abundant plants for cultivation",
B: "Limited market for agricultural products",
C: "Good roads and adequate capital.",
D: "Inadequate rainfall",
answer: "C. Good roads and adequate capital.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. On which river is the Victoria Falls?",
A: "Limpopo",
B: "Vaal",
C: "Zambezi",
D: "Orange",
answer: "C. Zambezi",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},


]